<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"><channel><title>health on Andy Dote</title><link>https://andydote.co.uk/tags/health/</link><description>Recent content in health on Andy Dote</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-gb</language><lastBuildDate>Sat, 08 Dec 2018 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://andydote.co.uk/tags/health/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Stopping Caring...</title><link>https://andydote.co.uk/2018/12/08/stopping-caring/</link><pubDate>Sat, 08 Dec 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://andydote.co.uk/2018/12/08/stopping-caring/</guid><description>&amp;hellip;about GitHub open source commit streak.
This is, I think, partially triggered by Marc Gravell&amp;rsquo;s post. I currently have had a GitHub commit streak going on 1878 days. The other night I realised, that I don&amp;rsquo;t care about it any more, and more so, I&amp;rsquo;m not sure why I did to start with.
I didn&amp;rsquo;t even mean to start doing it. I just noticed one day that I had done something every day for a couple of weeks, and vaguely wondered how long I could keep that up for.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>&hellip;about GitHub open source commit streak.</p>
<p>This is, I think, partially triggered by <a href="https://blog.marcgravell.com/2018/12/a-thanksgiving-carol.html">Marc Gravell&rsquo;s post</a>.  I currently <del>have</del> had a GitHub commit streak going on 1878 days.  The other night I realised, that I don&rsquo;t care about it any more, and more so, I&rsquo;m not sure why I did to start with.</p>
<p>I didn&rsquo;t even mean to start doing it.  I just noticed one day that I had done something every day for a couple of weeks, and vaguely wondered how long I could keep that up for.  It turns out the answer is &ldquo;quite a while&rdquo;.  For the most part, it was easy to do - just a small commit a day, it only takes a few minutes right?  But more and more often, I noticed that it was having a negative effect on <em>what</em> I was writing.</p>
<p>For instance, I wanted to learn about <a href="https://www.nomadproject.io/">Nomad</a>, but had been putting it off, as it wouldn&rsquo;t involve making any public commits.  So each time I came to start, I couldn&rsquo;t until I had done a public commit, and once that commit had was done, so was my motivation.  Which meant learning Nomad didn&rsquo;t happen for a long time.</p>
<p>It also affected what I did with old repositories on GitHub -  I wanted to remove some which serve no useful purpose any more, but I couldn&rsquo;t do that either, as that would remove their commits from the streak.  Likewise, I have a new version of my <a href="https://github.com/Pondidum/12factor-demo">TwelveFactor</a> repository, but I really should remove the old version. But doing so would remove the commits from the streak too.  So, as you might have guessed, I haven&rsquo;t done that either.  Maybe soon.  I have a lot of writing to go with it too.</p>
<p>On the subject of writing, that also suffered.  It takes a lot of effort to sit down and start writing a post, but usually, the words flow pretty smoothly once I am going.  But knowing I need to spare some energy for the commit of the day makes it even harder to start writing, so I just haven&rsquo;t been.  There are a lot of drafts with bullet-point lists waiting though, so maybe they will begin to see the light of day soon.</p>
<p>The irony is not lost on me that making this post will increase the commit count (GitHub pages based blog), so I am not committing (or finishing) this post until at least a day has passed.</p>
<p>I decided on the 7th December 2018 not to make any commits.  After that had happened - the act of deciding mind you, not the day itself, I felt a lot better.  I do not need to do anything. I can go and finish the book a friend recommended me.  I can spend my evenings learning about things I want to.  Or just do nothing some evenings.</p>
<p>No more worrying about public commits.  It&rsquo;s just not worth it.</p>
]]></content:encoded></item></channel></rss>