<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"><channel><title>feature flags on Andy Dote</title><link>https://andydote.co.uk/tags/feature-flags/</link><description>Recent content in feature flags on Andy Dote</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-gb</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 16 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://andydote.co.uk/tags/feature-flags/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Feature Flags in a CI Pipeline</title><link>https://andydote.co.uk/2023/01/16/feature-flags-ci/</link><pubDate>Mon, 16 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://andydote.co.uk/2023/01/16/feature-flags-ci/</guid><description>Feature flags are a great tool for helping software development; they provide controlled feature rollouts, facilitate A/B testing, and help decouple deployment from release. So when it comes to building our software, why do we treat the CI pipeline without the same level of engineering as the production code?
So, why not use feature flags in your CI pipeline?
TLDR Reduce the risk of breaking a CI pipeline for all of a project&amp;rsquo;s developers by using the flagon CLI to query Feature Flags, opting developers into and out of new CI features and processes by targeting groups of developers or branch naming patterns.</description></item><item><title>QA and Continuous Delivery</title><link>https://andydote.co.uk/2022/11/10/qa-and-continuous-delivery/</link><pubDate>Thu, 10 Nov 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://andydote.co.uk/2022/11/10/qa-and-continuous-delivery/</guid><description>When migrating to a continuous delivery process, it is often the case that a QA team are worried about what their role is going to be, and how the changes will affect the quality of the software in question.
While doing continuous delivery does change the QA process, when done well, it improves everyone&amp;rsquo;s lives and makes the software better quality. Are silver bullets incoming? Not quite, but we don&amp;rsquo;t have to make someone&amp;rsquo;s life worse to improve other people&amp;rsquo;s lives.</description></item><item><title>Deploy != Release</title><link>https://andydote.co.uk/2022/11/02/deploy-doesnt-mean-release/</link><pubDate>Wed, 02 Nov 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://andydote.co.uk/2022/11/02/deploy-doesnt-mean-release/</guid><description>Recently we were having a debate about release processes, and I wrote that deployments are not always equal to releases.
also deploy != release
—Andy, baiting discussion in Slack This turned out to be somewhat controversial until we discussed what I specifically meant by deploy and release.
As with all things, agreeing on definitions or understanding what someone means when they use a specific term is essential, so I thought I would write down a short blog post on it.</description></item><item><title>Feature Toggles: Reducing Coupling</title><link>https://andydote.co.uk/2019/06/11/feature-toggles-reducing-coupling/</link><pubDate>Tue, 11 Jun 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://andydote.co.uk/2019/06/11/feature-toggles-reducing-coupling/</guid><description>One of the points I make in my Feature Toggles talk is that you shouldn&amp;rsquo;t be querying a toggle&amp;rsquo;s status all over your codebase. Ideally, each toggle gets checked in as few places as possible - preferably only one place. The advantage of doing this is that very little of your codebase needs to be coupled to the toggles (either the toggle itself or the library/system for managing toggles itself).</description></item><item><title>Feature Toggles: Branch by Abstraction</title><link>https://andydote.co.uk/2019/06/03/feature-toggles-branch-by-abstraction/</link><pubDate>Mon, 03 Jun 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://andydote.co.uk/2019/06/03/feature-toggles-branch-by-abstraction/</guid><description>Recently, I was asked if I could provide an example of Branch By Abstraction when dealing with feature toggles. As this has come up a few times, I thought a blog post would be a good idea so I can refer others to it later too.
The Context As usual, this is some kind of backend (micro)service, and it will send email messages somehow. We will start with two implementations of message sending: the &amp;ldquo;current&amp;rdquo; version; which is synchronous, and a &amp;ldquo;new&amp;rdquo; version; which is async.</description></item><item><title>Feature Toggles with Consul</title><link>https://andydote.co.uk/2018/09/06/consul-feature-toggles/</link><pubDate>Thu, 06 Sep 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://andydote.co.uk/2018/09/06/consul-feature-toggles/</guid><description>Feature Toggles are a great way of helping to deliver working software, although there are a few things which could go wrong. See my talk Feature Toggles: The Good, The Bad and The Ugly for some interesting stories and insights on it!
I was talking with a colleague the other day about how you could go about implementing Feature Toggles in a centralised manner into an existing system, preferably with a little overhead as possible.</description></item></channel></rss>