<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"><channel><title>database on Andy Dote</title><link>https://andydote.co.uk/tags/database/</link><description>Recent content in database on Andy Dote</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-gb</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 04 Aug 2014 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://andydote.co.uk/tags/database/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Edge.js for Embedded Webuis</title><link>https://andydote.co.uk/2014/08/04/edgejs-for-embedded-webuis/</link><pubDate>Mon, 04 Aug 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://andydote.co.uk/2014/08/04/edgejs-for-embedded-webuis/</guid><description>We work we have a number of windows services which each have a lot of stats they could expose. Currently they are only interrogatable by the logfiles and from any notifications we receive.
I have been toying with the idea of hosting a website in-process which would give a simple dashboard ui and access to a live view of the log file. The idea first struck me when I was experimenting with FubuMvc, as they have an EmbeddedFubuMvcServer, which is very easy to use:</description></item><item><title>Configuring Dapper to work with custom types</title><link>https://andydote.co.uk/2014/07/22/configuring-dapper-to-work-with-custom-types/</link><pubDate>Tue, 22 Jul 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://andydote.co.uk/2014/07/22/configuring-dapper-to-work-with-custom-types/</guid><description>In the last post we looked at using custom ID types to help abstract the column type from the domain.
This works well until you start trying to load and save entities using an ORM, as the ORM has not way to know how to map a column to a custom type. ORMs provide extension points to allow you to create these mappings. As I tend to favour using Dapper, we will go through setting it up to work with our custom ID types.</description></item><item><title>Strong Type your entity IDs.</title><link>https://andydote.co.uk/2014/07/17/strong-type-your-entity-ids/</link><pubDate>Thu, 17 Jul 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://andydote.co.uk/2014/07/17/strong-type-your-entity-ids/</guid><description>The Database is just an Implementation Detail A quote from Martin Fowler given during his Architecture talk stated that the Database in your application should just be an implementation detail. I agree on this wholeheartedly and find that its really not that difficult to achieve if you think about your architecture carefully.
Having said that, I still see parts of the database implementation leaking out into the domain, mainly in the form of IDs.</description></item></channel></rss>