<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"><channel><title>logstash on Andy Dote</title><link>https://andydote.co.uk/tags/logstash/</link><description>Recent content in logstash on Andy Dote</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-gb</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 01 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://andydote.co.uk/tags/logstash/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Testing Immutable Infrastructure</title><link>https://andydote.co.uk/2019/01/01/immutable-infra/</link><pubDate>Tue, 01 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://andydote.co.uk/2019/01/01/immutable-infra/</guid><description>In my previous post, I glossed over one of the most important and useful parts of Immutable Infrastructure: Testability. There are many kinds of tests we can write for our infrastructure, but they should all be focused on the machine/service and maybe it&amp;rsquo;s nearest dependencies, not the entire system.
While this post focuses on testing a full machine (both locally in a VM, and remotely as an Amazon EC2 instance), it is also possible to do most of the same kind of tests against a Docker container.</description></item><item><title>Code-free tracing with LogStash and Jaeger</title><link>https://andydote.co.uk/2018/12/22/serilog-elk-jaeger/</link><pubDate>Sat, 22 Dec 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://andydote.co.uk/2018/12/22/serilog-elk-jaeger/</guid><description>I wanted to show request charts (similar to the network tab in firefox) for requests across our microservices but wanted to do so in the least invasive way possible.
We already use LogStash to collect logs from multiple hosts (via FileBeat) and forward them on to ElasticSearch, so perhaps I can do something to also output from LogStash to a tracing service.
There are a number of tracing services available (AppDash, Jaeger, Zipkin), but unfortunately LogStash doesn&amp;rsquo;t have plugins for any of them or for OpenTracing.</description></item></channel></rss>