<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"><channel><title>books on Andy Dote</title><link>https://andydote.co.uk/tags/books/</link><description>Recent content in books on Andy Dote</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-gb</language><lastBuildDate>Sat, 08 Dec 2018 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://andydote.co.uk/tags/books/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Stopping Caring...</title><link>https://andydote.co.uk/2018/12/08/stopping-caring/</link><pubDate>Sat, 08 Dec 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://andydote.co.uk/2018/12/08/stopping-caring/</guid><description>&amp;hellip;about GitHub open source commit streak.
This is, I think, partially triggered by Marc Gravell&amp;rsquo;s post. I currently have had a GitHub commit streak going on 1878 days. The other night I realised, that I don&amp;rsquo;t care about it any more, and more so, I&amp;rsquo;m not sure why I did to start with.
I didn&amp;rsquo;t even mean to start doing it. I just noticed one day that I had done something every day for a couple of weeks, and vaguely wondered how long I could keep that up for.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>&hellip;about GitHub open source commit streak.</p>
<p>This is, I think, partially triggered by <a href="https://blog.marcgravell.com/2018/12/a-thanksgiving-carol.html">Marc Gravell&rsquo;s post</a>.  I currently <del>have</del> had a GitHub commit streak going on 1878 days.  The other night I realised, that I don&rsquo;t care about it any more, and more so, I&rsquo;m not sure why I did to start with.</p>
<p>I didn&rsquo;t even mean to start doing it.  I just noticed one day that I had done something every day for a couple of weeks, and vaguely wondered how long I could keep that up for.  It turns out the answer is &ldquo;quite a while&rdquo;.  For the most part, it was easy to do - just a small commit a day, it only takes a few minutes right?  But more and more often, I noticed that it was having a negative effect on <em>what</em> I was writing.</p>
<p>For instance, I wanted to learn about <a href="https://www.nomadproject.io/">Nomad</a>, but had been putting it off, as it wouldn&rsquo;t involve making any public commits.  So each time I came to start, I couldn&rsquo;t until I had done a public commit, and once that commit had was done, so was my motivation.  Which meant learning Nomad didn&rsquo;t happen for a long time.</p>
<p>It also affected what I did with old repositories on GitHub -  I wanted to remove some which serve no useful purpose any more, but I couldn&rsquo;t do that either, as that would remove their commits from the streak.  Likewise, I have a new version of my <a href="https://github.com/Pondidum/12factor-demo">TwelveFactor</a> repository, but I really should remove the old version. But doing so would remove the commits from the streak too.  So, as you might have guessed, I haven&rsquo;t done that either.  Maybe soon.  I have a lot of writing to go with it too.</p>
<p>On the subject of writing, that also suffered.  It takes a lot of effort to sit down and start writing a post, but usually, the words flow pretty smoothly once I am going.  But knowing I need to spare some energy for the commit of the day makes it even harder to start writing, so I just haven&rsquo;t been.  There are a lot of drafts with bullet-point lists waiting though, so maybe they will begin to see the light of day soon.</p>
<p>The irony is not lost on me that making this post will increase the commit count (GitHub pages based blog), so I am not committing (or finishing) this post until at least a day has passed.</p>
<p>I decided on the 7th December 2018 not to make any commits.  After that had happened - the act of deciding mind you, not the day itself, I felt a lot better.  I do not need to do anything. I can go and finish the book a friend recommended me.  I can spend my evenings learning about things I want to.  Or just do nothing some evenings.</p>
<p>No more worrying about public commits.  It&rsquo;s just not worth it.</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>The Reading List</title><link>https://andydote.co.uk/2009/06/05/the-reading-list/</link><pubDate>Fri, 05 Jun 2009 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://andydote.co.uk/2009/06/05/the-reading-list/</guid><description>I have been meaning to write my own version of Jeff Atwood&amp;rsquo;s Reading List for a while now, and have finally managed to find some time to write about the books I have read.
Code Complete 2 I found this book quite tough reading. It wasn&amp;rsquo;t that it had nothing of use in it - far from it, it just was fairly heavy going. There are many things that can be learnt from this to help with the whole process of development, from how to name variables and functions to what the useful methods of development planning are.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I have been meaning to write my own version of Jeff Atwood&rsquo;s <a href="http://www.codinghorror.com/blog/archives/000020.html">Reading List</a> for a while now, and have finally managed to find some time to write about the books I have read.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.amazon.co.uk/Code-Complete-Practical-Handbook-Construction/dp/0735619670/ref=sr_1_1?ie=UTF8&amp;s=books&amp;qid=1244194043&amp;sr=8-1">Code Complete 2</a>
I found this book quite tough reading. It wasn&rsquo;t that it had nothing of use in it - far from it, it just was fairly heavy going.  There are many things that can be learnt from this to help with the whole process of development, from how to name variables and functions to what the useful methods of development planning are.  Highly recommended.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.amazon.co.uk/Dont-Make-Me-Think-Usability/dp/0321344758/ref=pd_sim_b_20">Don&rsquo;t Make Me Think</a>
This book by comparison was very easy to read.  It is fairly short (around four hours is plenty to read it) and is crammed with useful succinct information on design.  It is focused at web development, but 90% of the information applies to forms development too.  Highly Recommended.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.amazon.co.uk/Head-First-Design-Patterns-Freeman/dp/0596007124/ref=pd_sim_b_3">Head First Design Patterns</a>
I was about halfway though this book when I realised it was in Java and not C#&hellip;I thought the writers just had a healthy obsession with a particular type of Coffee!  In all seriousness though, this book is well written and provides the basics of each of the patterns covered and then builds on them.  It also compares similar patterns (like Monostate vs. Singleton).  Highly Recommended.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.amazon.co.uk/Refactoring-Improving-Design-Existing-Technology/dp/0201485672/ref=pd_sim_b_6">Refactoring: Improving the Design of Existing Code</a>
This is a useful, yet somewhat odd book.  The first few pages recommend how to read it (usually I just read a book start to finish&hellip;)  but with this one its recommended to read the first few chapters, read the titles of the next chapters and read the last chapter.  This is because the middle part is all of the different refactoring procedures.  Some of them seem so obvious (Sub method a block of code etc) but there are also some very useful techniques mentioned on how to look for areas to refactor, and what order things should be done in.  Recommended.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.amazon.co.uk/Mythical-Month-Essays-Software-Engineering/dp/0201835959/ref=pd_sim_b_29">The Mythical Man Month</a>
I learnt a lot from this book, mainly about the development lifecycle and team interaction.  The points brought up about Men and Months not being interchangeable has been particularly invaluable, as have the reasons behind why they are not interchangeable. Recommended</p>
<p><a href="http://www.amazon.co.uk/Windows-Forms-Programming-Chris-Sells/dp/0321267966/ref=sr_1_1?ie=UTF8&amp;s=books&amp;qid=1244194283&amp;sr=1-1">Windows Forms 2.0 Programming</a>
This is currently being read&hellip;</p>
]]></content:encoded></item></channel></rss>