<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"><channel><title>adr on Andy Dote</title><link>https://andydote.co.uk/tags/adr/</link><description>Recent content in adr on Andy Dote</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-gb</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 23 Jul 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://andydote.co.uk/tags/adr/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Architecture Testing</title><link>https://andydote.co.uk/2023/07/23/architecture-testing/</link><pubDate>Sun, 23 Jul 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://andydote.co.uk/2023/07/23/architecture-testing/</guid><description>One of the many reasons given for using microservices rather than a mono repository is that it enforces boundaries between services/modules. However, there are ways to achieve strong boundaries between modules/services in one repository, using tools which are already available: test runners.
Given a repository with the following structure:
. ├── libraries │ ├── core │ ├── events │ └── ui ├── services │ ├── catalogue │ ├── billing │ └── shipping └── tools └── admin-cli There are a few rules we should enforce:</description></item><item><title>How do you tag docker images?</title><link>https://andydote.co.uk/2021/11/10/docker-tagging/</link><pubDate>Wed, 10 Nov 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://andydote.co.uk/2021/11/10/docker-tagging/</guid><description>An interesting question came up at work today: how do you tag your Docker images? In previous projects, I&amp;rsquo;ve always used a short git sha, or sometimes a semver, but with no great consistency.
As luck would have it, I had pushed for a change in tagging format at a client not so long ago as the method we were using didn&amp;rsquo;t make a lot of sense and, worst of all, it was a manual process.</description></item><item><title>Architecture Decision Records</title><link>https://andydote.co.uk/2019/06/29/architecture-decision-records/</link><pubDate>Sat, 29 Jun 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://andydote.co.uk/2019/06/29/architecture-decision-records/</guid><description>This is a text version of a short talk (affectionately known as a &amp;ldquo;Coffee Bag&amp;rdquo;) I gave at work this week, on Architecture Design Records. You can see the slides here, but there isn&amp;rsquo;t a recording available, unfortunately.
It should be noted; these are not to replace full architecture diagrams; you should definitely still write C4 Models to cover the overall architecture. ADRs are for the details, such as serializer formats, convention-over-configuration details, number precisions for timings, or which metrics library is used and why.</description></item></channel></rss>