<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"><channel><title>process on Andy Dote</title><link>https://andydote.co.uk/tags/process/</link><description>Recent content in process on Andy Dote</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-gb</language><lastBuildDate>Sat, 29 Jun 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://andydote.co.uk/tags/process/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Architecture Decision Records</title><link>https://andydote.co.uk/2019/06/29/architecture-decision-records/</link><pubDate>Sat, 29 Jun 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://andydote.co.uk/2019/06/29/architecture-decision-records/</guid><description>This is a text version of a short talk (affectionately known as a &amp;ldquo;Coffee Bag&amp;rdquo;) I gave at work this week, on Architecture Design Records. You can see the slides here, but there isn&amp;rsquo;t a recording available, unfortunately.
It should be noted; these are not to replace full architecture diagrams; you should definitely still write C4 Models to cover the overall architecture. ADRs are for the details, such as serializer formats, convention-over-configuration details, number precisions for timings, or which metrics library is used and why.</description></item><item><title>Branching and Red Builds</title><link>https://andydote.co.uk/2018/08/10/red-builds/</link><pubDate>Fri, 10 Aug 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://andydote.co.uk/2018/08/10/red-builds/</guid><description>So this is a bit of a rant&amp;hellip;but hopefully with some solutions and workarounds too. So let&amp;rsquo;s kick things off with a nice statement:
I hate broken builds.
So everyone basically agrees on this point I think. The problem is that I mean all builds, including ones on shared feature branches.
Currently, I work on a number of projects which uses small(ish) feature branches. The way this works is that the team agrees on a new feature to work on creates a branch, and then each developer works on tasks, committing on their own branches, and Pull-Requesting to the feature branch.</description></item><item><title>Tweaking Processes to Remove Errors</title><link>https://andydote.co.uk/2017/12/09/tweaking-process-remove-errors/</link><pubDate>Sat, 09 Dec 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://andydote.co.uk/2017/12/09/tweaking-process-remove-errors/</guid><description>When we are developing (internal) Nuget packages at work, the process used is the following:
Get latest of master New branch feature-SomethingDescriptive Implement feature Push to GitHub TeamCity builds Publish package to the nuget feed Pull request Merge to master Obviously 3 to 6 can repeat many times if something doesn&amp;rsquo;t work out quite right.
There are a number of problems with this process:
Pull-request after publishing Pull requests are a great tool which we use extensively, but in this case, they are being done too late.</description></item><item><title>Evolutionary Development</title><link>https://andydote.co.uk/2017/11/17/evolutionary-development/</link><pubDate>Fri, 17 Nov 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://andydote.co.uk/2017/11/17/evolutionary-development/</guid><description>Having recently finished reading the Building Evolutionary Architectures: Support Constant Change book, I got to thinking about a system which was fairly representative of an architecture which was fine for it&amp;rsquo;s initial version, but it&amp;rsquo;s usage had outgrown the architecture.
Example System: Document Storage The system in question was a file store for a multi user, internal, desktop based CRM system. The number of users was very small, and the first implementation was just a network file share.</description></item></channel></rss>