<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"><channel><title>ioc on Andy Dote</title><link>https://andydote.co.uk/tags/ioc/</link><description>Recent content in ioc on Andy Dote</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-gb</language><lastBuildDate>Wed, 04 Oct 2017 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://andydote.co.uk/tags/ioc/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Composite Decorators with StructureMap</title><link>https://andydote.co.uk/2017/10/04/structuremap-composite-decorator/</link><pubDate>Wed, 04 Oct 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://andydote.co.uk/2017/10/04/structuremap-composite-decorator/</guid><description>While I was developing my Crispin project, I ended up needing to create a bunch of implementations of a single interface, and then use all those implementations at once (for metrics logging).
The interface looks like so:
public interface IStatisticsWriter { Task WriteCount(string format, params object[] parameters); } And we have a few implementations already:
LoggingStatisticsWriter - writes to an ILogger instance StatsdStatisticsWriter - pushes metrics to StatsD InternalStatisticsWriter - aggregates metrics for exposing via Crispin&amp;rsquo;s api To make all of these be used together, I created a fourth implementation, called CompositeStatisticsWriter (a name I made up, but apparently matches the Gang of Four definition of a composite!</description></item><item><title>Serilog LogContext with StructureMap and SimpleInjector</title><link>https://andydote.co.uk/2017/07/28/serilog-context-with-structuremap-and-simpleinjector/</link><pubDate>Fri, 28 Jul 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://andydote.co.uk/2017/07/28/serilog-context-with-structuremap-and-simpleinjector/</guid><description>This article has been updated after feedback from .Net Junkie (Godfather of SimpleInjector). I now have a working SimpleInjector implementation of this, and am very appreciative of him for taking the time to help me :)
Serilog is one of the main set of libraries I use on a regular basis, and while it is great at logging, it does cause something in our codebase that I am less happy about.</description></item></channel></rss>