<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"><channel><title>productivity on Andy Dote</title><link>https://andydote.co.uk/tags/productivity/</link><description>Recent content in productivity on Andy Dote</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-gb</language><lastBuildDate>Fri, 10 Aug 2018 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://andydote.co.uk/tags/productivity/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Branching and Red Builds</title><link>https://andydote.co.uk/2018/08/10/red-builds/</link><pubDate>Fri, 10 Aug 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://andydote.co.uk/2018/08/10/red-builds/</guid><description>So this is a bit of a rant&amp;hellip;but hopefully with some solutions and workarounds too. So let&amp;rsquo;s kick things off with a nice statement:
I hate broken builds.
So everyone basically agrees on this point I think. The problem is that I mean all builds, including ones on shared feature branches.
Currently, I work on a number of projects which uses small(ish) feature branches. The way this works is that the team agrees on a new feature to work on creates a branch, and then each developer works on tasks, committing on their own branches, and Pull-Requesting to the feature branch.</description></item><item><title>Writing Conference Talks</title><link>https://andydote.co.uk/2018/05/15/writing-conference-talks/</link><pubDate>Tue, 15 May 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://andydote.co.uk/2018/05/15/writing-conference-talks/</guid><description>I saw an interesting question on twitter today:
Hey, people who talk at things: How long does it take you to put a new talk together?
I need like 50 hours over at least a couple of months to make something I don&amp;rsquo;t hate. I&amp;rsquo;m trying to get that down (maybe by not doing pictures?) but wondering what&amp;rsquo;s normal for everyone else.
Source
I don&amp;rsquo;t know how long it takes me to write a talk - as it is usually spread over many weeks/months, worked on as and when I have inspiration.</description></item><item><title>Getting Things Done</title><link>https://andydote.co.uk/2017/07/15/getting-things-done/</link><pubDate>Sat, 15 Jul 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://andydote.co.uk/2017/07/15/getting-things-done/</guid><description>I have been trying to actually be productive in my evenings and weekends, but I find I often end up not getting as much done as I feel I could have. I end up browsing imgur, reading slashdot, reddit, twitter, etc. rather than reading books, writing or anything else.
The first point doesn&amp;rsquo;t fit in anywhere else, but somewhere I saw a tip about keeping a house clean (I think):</description></item></channel></rss>